<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % oro_ents SYSTEM "http://people.mech.kuleuven.be/~psoetens/orocos/doc/orocos.ent" >
%oro_ents;
]
>

<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>The TaskBrowser Component</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
	<firstname>Peter</firstname>
	<surname>Soetens</surname>
	<affiliation>
	  <orgname>FMTC</orgname>
	  <address><country>Belgium</country></address>
	</affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>
      <holder>Peter Soetens, FMTC</holder>
    </copyright>

    <abstract>
      <para>
	This document explains the design and implementation of the
	<emphasis>Core Library</emphasis> of &orocos;, the <emphasis>Open
	RObot COntrol Software</emphasis> project. The CoreLib provides
	infrastructural support for the functional and application components
	of the &orocos; framework.
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>0.24.0</revnumber>
	<date>16 June 2006</date>
	<authorinitials>ps</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Introduction.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
	under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
	any later version published by the Free Software Foundation, with no
	Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
	Texts. A copy of this license can be found at
	<ulink
	  url="http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/fdl.html">http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This document describes the TaskBrowser Orocos component for
      user interaction with other components. It can visit any
      component in a given network, query it, send it commands,
      run programs etc.
    </para>
    <section>Principle</section>
    <para>
      Each Orocos component has a standard interface of properties,
      events, commands etc. It is possible to query and use this interface
      generically. The TaskBrowser is connected to one component only
      at a time. It can however be used to 'browse' the network of
      peer components and visit any component in an application.
    </para>
    <para>
      The TaskBrowser is a component itself, but it offers a 'window'
      to another component. When it is connected
      to another component, it dynamically creates the 'anti' 
      data ports and connects these to the other component. In
      this way, the TaskBrowser can send data to any component.
      When the component is left, the ports are disconnected and
      removed.
    </para>
    <figure><title>Task Browsing</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="taskbrowsing" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption><para>The TaskBrowser is initially connected to a
      component. It can 'enter' a component, which shows a perspective
      from 'within' the component. it can 'leave' a component which
      shows a perspective from outside the component. The 'cd' command
      allows to visit other components.
      </para></caption>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      There are two possible views on a component: from inside the component,
      as a program inside the component sees the component interface, or
      from outside the component, as a peer component sees the component 
      interface. The Taskbrowser can offer the user both views, allowing
      maximum interactivity. In both views, the component network can be
      browsed.
    </para>
  </section>
</article>